Finding Aid for Judson L. Austin Papers 1862-1865
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Judson L. Austin Papers 1862-1865
Austin, Judson L.
Resident of Chesire, Allegan County, Mich., who served in Company B, 19th Michigan Infantry, during the Civil War. Extensive and detailed letters, chiefly to his wife, describing his military experiences, including the battle of Thompson's Station, where his regiment surrendered, the siege of Atlanta, and Sherman's campaigns in Georgia and South and North Carolina.
004; mf357c,mf358c
2 microfilms
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The original papers and partial transcripts were acquired in 1972 and 1981 from Nina L. Ness (Donor no. 4567 ). The complete transcripts and indexing were acquired in 1990 from David J. Holquist (Donor no. 7591 ).
The collection is open for research.
Judson L. Austin was born in 1836. A resident of Cheshire, Allegan Co., Michigan, Austin enlisted in Company B of the Nineteenth Michigan Infantry on August 13, 1862 at Allegan and mustered in September 5, 1862. Austin married Sarah E. Colburn, also of Allegan County, Michigan.
The Nineteenth Michigan participated in the action with Bragg's cavalry forces at Spring Hill, Thompson's Station, Tennessee, on March 5, 1863, during which Austin was with his older brother, Pack, who died on the battlefield. Most of the regiment was captured and marched south to Libby Prison. Although the regiment was exchanged May 25, 1863, Austin was released early along with other sick and wounded prisoners, and by April 2, 1863 he was at the U.S. General Hospital in Annapolis, Maryland. He received a furlough about April 30, 1863, which he spent visiting his family in Michigan.
Austin returned to the regiment when it reorganized in early June 1863 at Camp Chase, Ohio. The Nineteenth Michigan was stationed in Tennessee from June 1863-May 1864. The regiment then participated in the Atlanta Campaign and Occupation, May-November 1864; the March to the Sea, November-December 1864; and the Campaign of the Carolinas, January-April 1865; making their final march to Washington, D.C., in April-May 1865. The Nineteenth Michigan marched in the Grand Review on May 24, 1865. Austin was mustered out May 26, 1865 at McDougall Hospital, New York Harbor.
After his discharge, Austin returned to Allegan County, Michigan, where he resumed farming in Trowbridge Township. He and Sarah had three children, George A. (probably born in early 1863), Benjamin B. and Frederick P. Austin.
The collection consists of approximately 300 letters written by Austin, chiefly to his young wife, Sarah. Austin's letters are rich in details about his military experiences, particularly in the areas of war maneuvers and events, officers and doctors, rebels and the South, and descriptions of camp life, as well as comments about the homefront and advice to Sarah and other family members at home. The letters are arranged chronologically.
In 1990 Professor David J. Holquist of Calvin College, Grand Rapids, Michigan, added to the Austin Papers a set of complete transcripts of the letters, as well as a detailed index of topics mentioned in the letters. For easy reference, each letter has been assigned a number code based on the folder number, followed by the number of the letter's chronological order within the folder, e.g., the 4th (fourth) letter in Folder 15 is #15-4. The topical index is located at the end of this finding aid.
Subjects:
Austin, Judson L.; United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 19th (1862-1865). Company B.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Kentucky--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Tennessee--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Maryland--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Ohio--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Georgia--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; South Carolina--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; North Carolina--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Contributors:
Holquist, David J.; Ness, Nina L.
- Correspondence
  - Topical Index (Reel 1)
    (The index prepared by Professor Holquist appears at the beginning of Roll 1. It is also included at the end of this finding aid. The 25 letters from the 1981 accession (originally folder 15-a) are included in the full transcripts, but are not included in the topical index.)
  - Undated and fragments (Reel 1, Folder 1)
  - 1862
    - January-September and undated 1862 (Reel 1, Folder 2)
    - October-December 1862 (Reel 1, Folder 3)
  - 1863
    - January-February 1863 (Reel 1, Folder 4)
    - March-June 1863 (Reel 1, Folder 5)
    - July-August 1863 (Reel 1, Folder 6)
    - September-October 1863 (Reel 1, Folder 7)
    - November-December 1863 (Reel 1, Folder 8)
    - Undated and fragments (Reel 1, Folder 9)
  - 1864
    - January-February and undated 1864 (Reel 1, Folder 10)
    - March-April 1864 (Reel 1, Folder 11)
    - May-June 1864 (Reel 1, Folder 12)
    - July-August 1864 (Reel 1, Folder 13)
    - September-December 1864 (Reel 1, Folder 14)
  - January-May 1865 (Reel 2, Folder 15)
- Transcripts correspondence
  - Full transcripts prepared by Prof. David J. Holquist (Reel 2)
  - Partial transcripts prepared primarily by Nina L. Ness, 2 folders (Reel 2)
Partial Index to Judson L. Austin Correspondence
Each letter has been assigned a number code based on the folder number, followed by the number of the letter's chronological order within the folder, e.g., the 4th (fourth) letter in Folder 15 is #15-4.
Camp life
(Comments on food,sickness,interpersonal relations, discipline, and the layout of camps):
1-1; 1-3; 1-4; 1-5; 1-8; 1-10; 1-12; 1-13
2-1; 2-2; 2-3; 2-5; 2-6; 2-7; 2-8; 2-9; 2-10
3-1; 3-2; 3-3; 3-5; 3-6; 3-8; 3-9; 3-10; 3-11; 3-12; 3-13; 3-14; 3-15; 3-16; 3-17; 3-18; 3-19; 3-21; 3-22; 3-23; 3-25; 3-27; 3-28; 3-29
4-1; 4-2; 4-3; 4-4; 4-5; 4-6; 4-7; 4-8; 4-9; 4-10; 4-13; 4-14; 4-16
5-14; 5-18; 5-19; 5-25
6-1; 6-3; 6-4; 6-5; 6-7; 6-9; 6-10; 6-11; 6-12; 6-13; 6-14; 6-15; 6-16; 6-17; 6-18; 6-19; 6-20; 6-21; 6-22; 6-23; 6-25; 6-26; 6-27; 6-28
7-1; 7-3; 7-5; 7-7; 7-9; 7-10; 7-11; 7-13; 7-15; 7-16; 7-18; 7-19
8-1; 8-2; 8-3; 8-4; 8-5; 8-6; 8-8; 8-9; 8-10; 8-11; 8-12; 8-14; 8-17
9-2; 9-3; 9-4; 9-5; 9-7; 9-8; 9-11; 9-12
10-1; 10-2; 10-3; 10-6; 10-9; 10-10; 10-11; 10-12; 10-13; 10-14; 10-15; 10-17; 10-19; 10-20
11-1; 11-2; 11-3; 11-4; 11-6; 11-13; 11-14; 11-15; 11-16
12-4; 12-5; 12-8; 12-10; 12-12; 12-15; 13-2
13-4; 13-5; 13-6; 13-8; 13-11; 13-16; 13-17; 13-18; 14-2
14-3; 14-4; 14-6; 14-7; 14-8; 14-9; 14-11; 14-13; 14-15; 14-17; 14-19; 14-20
15-1; 15-2; 15-4; 15-6; 15-9; 15-20; 15-21; 15-22; 15-29
Death
(Comments and observations on death):
1-4; 1-9; 1-13; 2-10
3-20; 3-23; 3-25; 3-27; 4-7; 4-13; 4-15; 5-24; 6-16; 7-7; 7-10
9-4; 9-6; 9-13; 10-8; 11-5; 11-7; 12-1; 12-2; 12-4; 12-5
13-7; 13-8; 13-9; 13-11; 13-14; 13-15; 13-17; 14-10; 15-14; 15-22
Deserters
3-2; 3-18; 3-22; 4-12; 4-13; 4-16; 6-8; 6-18; 15-3; 15-10; 15-19
Equipment and Pay
(Comments on amount and regularity of pay and condition and supply of equipment such as uniforms, tents, blankets, guns and ammunition):
2-6; 2-9; 3-19; 3-22; 4-1; 4-2; 4-5; 4-12; 4-15; 6-13; 6-2; 8-9; 8-12
12-4; 12-5; 12-10; 12-12; 13-4; 13-5; 13-18; 14-6; 14-7; 14-12; 14-13; 14-16; 14-17; 14-18; 14-20; 15-12; 15-17
Homefront
(General comments on events at home, expressions of homesickness, advise on events, references to people at home and to soldiers from home, comments on the draft, and the public attitude toward the war):
1-2; 1-6; 1-7; 1-9; 1-12; 2-3; 2-5; 2-6; 2-11; 3-10; 3-15; 3-17; 3-25
4-12; 4-14; 4-17; 5-9; 5-10; 5-11; 5-16; 5-20; 5-23; 5-26; 6-1; 6-2; 6-3; 6-7; 6-12; 6-14; 6-19; 6-20; 6-24; 6-25; 6-26; 6-27; 6-28; 7-2; 7-4; 7-7; 7-8; 7-9; 7-13; 7-16
8-1; 8-3; 8-6; 8-7; 8-8; 8-11; 8-12; 8-13; 8-15; 8-16; 8-18; 9-5; 9-7; 9-8; 9-10; 9-11; 9-12; 9-13
10-4; 10-5; 10-6; 10-7; 10-8; 10-9; 10-11; 10-12; 10-13; 10-16; 10-17; 10-18; 10-19; 10-20; 11-2; 11-5; 11-7; 11-11; 11-12; 11-14; 11-15
12-2; 12-6; 12-7; 12-10; 12-11; 12-13; 12-14; 12-15; 12-18; 13-1; 13-6; 13-9; 13-11; 13-12; 13-13; 13-15; 13-16; 13-17; 13-18
14-2; 14-3; 14-4; 14-5; 14-6; 14-7; 14-8; 14-9; 14-10; 14-12; 14-13; 14-15; 14-16; 14-18; 14-19; 14-20
15-1; 15-2; 15-3; 15-4; 15-5; 15-6; 15-7; 15-9; 15-11; 15-12; 15-13; 15-14; 15-15; 15-16; 15-17; 15-18; 15-19; 15-21; 15-22; 15-23
Hospital
(Comments on experiences in both Northern and Southern hospitals):
5-7; 5-8; 5-10; 5-11; 5-12; 15-24; 15-25; 15-26; 15-27; 15-28
In Combat
5-0b; 12-5; 12-9; 12-15; 12-16; 12-17; 13-1; 13-3; 13-4; 13-7; 13-8; 13-11; 13-12; 13-13; 13-14; 13-15; 13-17; 14-17; 14-18; 15-10; 15-14
Inter-Union Army Rivalry
14-1; 15-27
Lincoln, Abraham
(Comments on and references to Lincoln):
1-10; 2-9; 3-26; 6-8; 11-5; 11-14; 12-10; 14-6; 14-15; 15-20
Negroes in the Civil War
(Comments on and attitude toward both slaves and freed blacks as well as black soldiers):
1-8; 2-3; 3-12; 3-14; 3-17; 3-18; 3-20; 3-21; 3-24; 3-26; 4-4; 4-13; 6-17; 6-22; 7-6; 7-7; 7-10; 8-3; 8-4; 11-6; 11-13; 13-5; 13-9; 14-1; 14-15; 14-17; 15-16
New York City Draft Riots
(Comments and observations on the New York City Draft riots and on New York City):
6-8; 11-15; 15-27; 15-28
Officers and Doctors
(Expressed opinions of both officers and doctors, comments on their abilities and failings, good and bad characteristics, etc):
1-13; 2-1; 2-2; 2-9; 3-6; 3-7; 3-15; 3-17; 3-29; 4-1; 4-4; 4-6; 4-8; 4-9; 4-13; 5-21; 5-26; 6-1; 6-6; 6-9; 6-10; 6-17; 6-25
7-7; 7-16; 8-4; 8-6; 9-1; 9-4; 9-5; 9-6; 9-12; 10-9; 11-8; 11-13; 11-17; 12-4; 12-5; 12-9
13-9; 13-13; 13-14; 13-16; 14-1; 14-9; 15-1; 15-2; 15-4; 15-13; 15-19; 15-27
Politics and Elections
1-5; 4-13; 8-9; 11-12; 11-17; 12-10; 14-6; 14-15
Prisoner
(Personal recollections on being held captive by the Southern Army):
5-0b; 5-1; 5-2; 5-3; 5-4; 5-6; 8-11; 11-2; 11-13; 11-17; 14-5
Rebels, Contacts with
1-3; 1-5; 1-9; 1-10; 2-1; 2-3; 2-8; 2-11; 3-7; 3-12; 3-17; 3-20; 4-11; 4-12; 4-15; 5-15; 5-24
6-2; 6-9; 6-26; 7-2; 7-5; 7-6; 7-9; 7-10; 7-11; 7-12; 7-13; 7-17; 7-19; 8-2; 8-4; 8-5; 8-8; 8-17; 9-1; 9-6
10-2; 10-6; 10-8; 10-10; 10-18; 11-11; 11-14; 12-3; 12-4; 12-5; 12-9; 12-10; 12-12; 12-13; 12-15; 12-16; 12-17; 12-18
13-1; 13-2; 13-3; 13-5; 13-6; 13-7; 13-8; 13-9; 13-11; 13-12; 13-13; 13-14; 13-15; 13-17; 13-18
14-1; 14-5; 14-6; 14-7; 14-11; 14-16; 14-17; 14-18; 15-2; 15-9; 15-10; 15-14; 15-16; 15-21
Sex
(Comments on and the availability of sex, etc):
6-19; 6-26; 8-17; 8-18; 10-12; 10-20; 11-3; 11-13
The South
(General comments on the Southern secession and rebellion, war in general, also observations of the South and its people):
1-5; 1-7; 2-3; 3-8; 3-12; 3-18; 3-19; 3-21; 3-24; 4-6; 4-13; 4-16; 5-18; 6-1; 6-10; 6-17; 7-9; 7-10; 7-12; 7-19
8-1; 8-2; 9-8; 9-10; 10-3; 10-6; 10-11; 10-13; 10-16; 11-1; 11-6; 11-9; 11-13; 11-15; 11-17; 12-1; 12-3; 12-5; 12-9
13-7; 13-8; 13-9; 13-11; 13-14; 14-1; 14-2; 14-3; 14-5; 14-7; 14-15; 14-17; 14-19; 14-20; 15-2; 15-6; 15-10; 15-16; 15-19
Southern Prisoners
(Comments on the attitude toward and treatment of Southern Prisoners):
3-3; 3-5; 3-7; 4-1; 4-15; 6-1; 6-9; 6-10; 7-6; 7-10; 7-11; 7-13; 8-8; 10-6; 10-13; 11-8; 11-14; 12-5; 13-7; 14-5; 14-16; 15-17; 15-21
War Maneuvers
2-1; 2-9; 3-5; 3-14; 3-17; 3-18; 3-20; 3-26; 3-27; 3-28; 4-1; 4-3; 4-9; 4-11; 4-12; 4-13; 4-15; 4-17; 5-17; 5-18; 5-22; 5-25; 5-27
6-4; 6-5; 6-9; 6-11; 6-14; 6-16; 6-23; 6-25; 7-5; 7-6; 7-10; 7-11; 7-12; 7-13; 7-17; 7-18; 7-19; 8-1; 8-4; 8-10; 9-1; 9-6; 10-1
10-13; 10-19; 11-1; 11-4; 11-11; 11-15; 11-16; 11-17; 12-1; 12-2; 12-4; 12-5; 12-7; 12-8; 12-9; 12-12; 12-16; 12-17
13-2; 13-3; 13-4; 13-5; 13-7; 13-8; 13-9; 13-10; 13-11; 13-13; 13-14; 13-15; 13-17; 13-18; 14-2
14-3; 14-6; 14-7; 14-9; 14-11; 14-13; 14-14; 14-15; 14-16; 14-17; 14-18; 14-19; 15-2
15-6; 15-8; 15-10; 15-11; 15-14; 15-16; 15-17; 15-19; 15-21; 15-23
War News & Events
2-11; 3-12; 3-17; 3-18; 3-20; 3-21; 3-22; 3-24; 3-26; 3-28; 4-1; 4-2; 4-3; 4-5; 4-9; 4-11; 4-12; 4-13; 4-14; 4-15; 4-17
5-27; 6-1; 6-4; 6-7; 6-8; 6-14; 6-16; 6-20; 6-21; 6-23; 7-3; 7-5; 7-6; 7-9; 7-10; 7-11; 7-12; 7-13; 7-14; 7-16; 7-17; 7-18
8-3; 8-6; 8-9; 8-11; 8-12; 8-13; 8-16; 9-1; 9-2; 9-6; 9-9; 9-10; 10-11 10-10; 10-12; 11-9; 11-10; 11-11; 11-15; 12-3; 12-5; 12-9; 12-10
13-1; 13-8; 13-11; 13-14; 13-15; 13-16; 13-18; 14-1; 14-2; 14-3; 14-5; 14-6; 14-8; 14-15; 14-19
15-1; 15-6; 15-8; 15-19; 15-20; 15-21; 15-23; 15-25